hello and welcome it's July 29th 2023
and we're here in session three
discussion
of the course physics this information
processing at the Active inference
Institute
we're having a follow-up discussion on
Chris fields's third lecture on Quantum
reference frames
and we're looking forward to your
participation so if you're watching
along live and you've been invited to
the calendar event it's not too late to
jump in if you're watching on YouTube
you can write any questions or comments
in the live chat with Dean and Andrew
here we're going to be looking at some
of the key points and taking it in a few
different directions sharing our
reference frames making a shared one so
enter be awesome to
have you zoom in a little bit on the
slide and then
feel free to to take us through some of
the key points so that we can
um see a little bit how you're seeing it
thank you
that looks good yep
okay so let's let's start by reviewing
um
the last lecture from a couple weeks ago
and then we can open up the discussions
if there's any questions that appear in
the live chat we can address those
uh all right so
lecture two Chris introduced this idea
of uh
the information processing between
system amb you know where they interact
via qubits on a boundary and they have
um reference frames
that give meaning to this com to this
communication you want to think of uh
information processing as a
communication Channel
uh the way
um Shannon thought about it uh so that
was the lecture too
and lecture three a couple weeks ago
uh try to make this more explicit
by emphasizing the idea that this has to
be
physically embodied somewhere okay and I
I think that because we are so used to
information being fungible
in no small part because of the internet
and everything uh it's it's a little
hard
uh to understand at first when the
claims made that you have a qri that
it's non-fungible or you have a piece of
quantum information that's not fungible
or things like the no cloning theorem
we're so used information being
punishable to it being zeros and ones
that
it's a bit of a change in in mindset at
first but that's exactly what lecture
three
um introduced this was all all stuff
right um could you maybe just unpack
that a little bit what would it mean for
information to be fungible or what's
that stance like and then what does it
mean for information to be non-fungible
and what is that stance like
yeah I'm about to get there uh so let me
let me scroll down the slides um because
that's addressed here so I was maybe I
should have kept this uh in the
beginning but anyways session two talked
about how information Theory makes this
simple and obvious okay
yeah
session three we talk about reference
frames and mechanistically how all of
this works
um so yeah let's address that question
of the difference between
hold on one second let me
use my mouse to scroll down here
okay so that's that's a little faster
right
okay so
um
can you restate your question uh Daniel
yeah what would it mean for information
to be fungible or non-fungible
people might be familiar with that in
the economic setting with non-fungible
tokens and all of that but what are we
talking about with informational
fungibility
I I think it basically comes down to
um to whether you can replicate I mean
it's basically the difference between
classical and Quantum information as far
as I know uh
uh uh fungible information is everything
that you can basically turn into a
message of zeros and ones
uh
it's you know how you transmit it maybe
different you know the channel the
physical hardware and so on but but at
the end of the day
it's something that you can write on a
boundary and something that you can
transmit at zero seven ones whereas
Quantum information
[Music]
um you literally have to send the
hardware the piece of Hardware uh the
qrf at least that's how I understand it
so a simple answer might be
um that it's
information encoded in a piece of
software versus a piece of Hardware but
I I don't I don't think that analogy is
perfect
but what do you
yeah Dean what do you think
well here's what I'm curious about
and again you guys can help me with this
as opposed to reference frames I
oftentimes
default to frame of reference and I know
then one of the live streams what I
tried to bring out was the idea that
there was an ice cream cone looking in
an ice cream truck and the question was
always whether or not which which one of
those two entities is one is in the
foreground and one is in the background
and in this slide that Ander has a the
question is is the non-fungibility
because
only A and B can decide whether the a
the VA as seen by B the a is deeper
into that image be based on our frame of
reference and the B is closer or is the
B the one that's actually deeper and the
a is the one that's in the foreground
and I was wondering whether the idea of
non-copyability is because of that depth
of field aspect that cannot be
determined unless it's literally handed
over
the way that Chris was describing it
I think I think that's basically
accurate I think
um I'm not sure I can answer the
question but I think I have the feeling
that Chris
well Chris said this in the lecture that
I mean
is somewhere in your your nervous system
and uh here whether I mean you bring up
a good point right it looks like this
slide is a bit of a an optical illusion
whether you see A or B deeper uh I guess
it depends on something going on inside
your head
um if you this picture is so symmetrical
that if you focus on albumin you can
change your opinion
um what would just to even
connect that to what we're talking about
the classical fungible information on
the holographic screen on the blanket
and then the quantum cognitive rotation
is those two images
are on the screen identical and then
whether it gets a Quantum rotation such
that the uh three points of the axes are
closer to us than the intersection on
that kind of tetrahedron or the other
way around whether the ballerina is
rotating one way or the other that's not
on the boundary so the information about
the depth of field
is part of the qrf or part of the
enactment of the qrf and it's not
written on the boundary
and that goes back to the preparation
question and not just the measuring yeah
like if the preparation if your whole
enculturation or the last five minutes
it was uh entrained or you were holding
an object that predisposed you to think
that the vertex of the intersection was
further away
that's the preparation that's your
that's your prior so that when you get
this ambiguous artifact you rotate it
into the most natural
position cognitively
and that's the preparation that sets you
up for measurement no measurement can
happen without a preparation
what do you think Andrew
uh sure yeah
everything is that makes sense
[Music]
um
so uh perhaps let me
uh
let me recall what was that around the
slides uh there was a
in this whole Spirit or philosophy of
making
emphasizing on information is physical
you know inconcubing this whole thing
for me
um one of the
aglarian emissions in in physics was
the embodiment of
the reference frame which was treated as
an abstraction
um you know in classical physics
such as by galindale but maybe even
Einstein even if he my hunch is that he
did have more of this Instinct of you
know particularly in all those thought
experiments of trying to chase the
library
you are chasing the library right so at
the end of the day
um but I mean this this is a whole
process of making the Observer and the
reference frame more and more explicit
and more and more physical
because at the end of the day it has to
right if if you start with this
assumption that
um
solipsistic assumption almost that you
know all you see and and you know is is
part of the same material uh ether that
you are then you know
then you are part of the universe that
in Europe serving something that is out
there uh so you need to make include a
theory of what it means for you to be
observing that right and at the end of
the day the Observer has to be physical
that's what was emphasized by by Chris
at the beginning of this lecture
so this jump from treating the reference
frame as an abstraction
to a real physical entity
and
yeah these are
these people have uh
about uh
in these papers that are ordered there
but I should also remark
uh if folks want to see this it's it's
coming up in high energy Theory also in
the recent work of
um in recent work of saskins and others
where they talk about Quantum reference
traits uh very explicit so I don't I
don't have the citations off the bat but
it's definitely becoming an important
thing in the last 20 years this attempt
to really explicitly treat the reference
frame on the Observer asset Quantum
entity uh as a physical entity
okay so this
that's what I just said okay the jump
from treating things reference rooms as
abstractions to physical objects
go
and
and because we cannot make
a perfect copy of quantum information we
say that these are unique and clonable
and unfungible
um so
in order to recreate an experiment
perfectly uh this is the this is the
address as a part of fungibility or not
right Canalis if you have some sort of
Quantum experiment and Analysis involved
are you know it's the usual
DPR uh thought experiment or whatever
Alice involved are separated by light
years
is it enough if you want to recreate the
same exact the same experiment for Alice
to send
string of zeros and ones
well
[Music]
if you had an experiment where that's
enough then then you can recreate it
with tangible information if not
then you need to somehow send
non-tangible information which really
implies in a piece of hardware
um can I can I add another uh another
piece here look on the previous uh slide
so
this looks really Technical and
scientific but let's think about Alice's
laboratory is Alice's brain mind and
Bob's analogously Alice is thinking
about what to say and then says it and
that information might be written in a
chat form it might be said verbally it
might be transmitted through digital or
analog signal but at some point it's
going through this classical
informational interface and then Bob's
laboratory is like perceiving and
unpacking it and the question of
semantic alignment is such that if Alice
gives a shopping list of 10 items if
there's semantic alignment Bob would be
able to go to the store and then find
those 10 items and it made me think of
the the dictionary definition of left
and right so this gets back to our
discussion of whether the vertex on
these axes is coming towards us or away
from us so I looked up the dictionary
definition of left
on towards or relating to the side of a
human body or of a thing that is to the
West when the person or that thing is
facing north so that's I guess one
attempt to Anchor what it means to be
left the second definition is the left
hand part side or direction and you
could imagine there's an analogous
definition for right the point is you
can't describe verbally
leftness and rightness or chirality in
general
because its reference is an embodied
perspective
and so if Alice said okay you're gonna
go down the street and then turn left at
the stop sign
how would Alice communicate to Bob
what leftness meant at that stop sign
versus rightness
and that's this question of flipping
and the way that the quantum formalism
accommodates that is through the wick
rotation and the quantum cognitive
events where the fungible
transmittable holographic information
gets rotated into the imaginary axis
with the formalisms that enable it to be
rotated at all but that means you could
rotate it left quote or rotate it right
yeah I think that's
that's a very good explanation I don't
know if I have much to add Dean you
wanted to say something
well so but
I can't I don't know the answer to this
but to take what Daniel just said to
take the basic
concept of being able to
take something that for all intents and
purposes can appear one way or another
and then turn that into how Chris closed
the last lecture with
we are we are seeing ourselves as both
being entangled
and also
being separatable how did we go
literally from a three-dimension Vertex
to we are both entangled and we're we're
not living in a paradox that's just the
way it is we're also
removing ourselves or separating
ourselves at the same time that's what I
would like to know because
somewhere between
three arbitrary lines and complexity is
not a paradox
something has to be happening and I'm
not exactly sure how that transition
plays out
anybody want to enlighten me
can you repeat your question please well
how do we how do we go like from at this
point of the reference frame
description of saying it can't
you you can't copy it all you can do is
pass it
because we think things could be flipped
based on internal
internal reference frames internal
meanings and internal models the thing
we choose for context
goes all the way out to the conclusion
of and uh of Chris's
um conversation with us in in number
three where he said
bottom line is is that it's not a
paradox that as Things become more and
more complex
then it it wants to be able it it wants
to get to a place of entanglement
alignment a sense of agreement and at
the same time wants to remain separate
so between those two things
a whole lot has happened but and I don't
think we've skipped over it but we
certainly haven't
opened it up and really looked at it
closely and I'm just curious what's in
between those two scales
I I agree I think we're we're gonna
cover that towards the end of the of the
talk um
but I agree I I don't know how you see
this related to qrs uh or the stuff we
just talked about but I think it's the
big question in this in this lecture
right that was like where does this
tension between
increase in complexity and you know
wanting wanting to predict what the
environment is doing what one requires
separability at least colloquially
speaking I I think this tension
is
um
basically what the free energy principle
comes down to right Daniel what do you
think
you have the free energy and you have
the E minus TS
one is prediction error I mean not
exactly e minus TS right that would be
thermodynamics but you know one is
prediction error and the other one is
what was it
I can't remember
I'll definitely look forward to the the
technical unpacking that that you'll get
to soon but but I was reminded of the
William Blake quotation do what you will
this Life's a fiction and is made up of
contradiction
so let's modify that
um project what you will rotate what you
will space times a fiction
not that it's false but that it's a
projected fictionalization that it
doesn't have the ontological Primacy
that the topology of communication does
and is made up of contradiction yes and
it's made up of this tension between
fitting and not overfitting between
aligning and the principle of unitarity
and differentiating and becoming through
others we become ourselves and that type
of articulation and uh recognizing that
two complementary forces like convex and
concave come into existence at once like
a zero to two jump
is not an issue or or a stumbling block
it's that we wouldn't have it any other
way
couldn't have it any other way
yeah uh sure we'll get that towards the
end uh you can almost even call it a
duality it's not uh far-fetched I mean
it's it's the sort of thing that I think
most people will be happy to take for
granted such you know super symmetry
like you have
two kinds of particles but the same
amount of them and you know dualities
are all over the place so I I think I
think it's fairly it's not unreasonable
to just accept that there are there is a
tension between uh increasing complexity
which
you want you want AME to be separable
for and
accuracy prediction now how this is
related to
um emergent space and uh on this curves
stuff you know I I don't want to make
very part fetch claims we'll talk about
emergent space later on the course uh
but but for now let's let's say a few
more words about carefs and then we'll
get to the the complexity stuff towards
the end
um
so
so qrfs are almost building blocks if
you want or
uh
information processing uh here it's very
uh useful to recall definition that I
feel I think we we have
mentioned before
of information as being differences that
make a difference that's probably the
best colloquial definition of
information I've heard and I think
I think it does a lot of work I mean
it's almost mathematical but anyways we
need to unpack it a little more and and
see so
for a difference to make a difference
what do you want out of qrf right
and surprisingly I mean not surprisingly
but
reassuringly I think would be the work
uh
you need a qrf to have sensory
action
and a default state right this is sort
of like uh where your basing prior
distribution is encoded these three
things
we'll give you a building block for any
information processing and that you know
ties together with all the work in the
free energy literature
and perception action loops and and
whatnot
um so before we see mathematically
poetry RF is defined
uh I think it's more illustrative and I
think Chris went exactly on the right
order when when he presented this a
couple weeks ago
teen uh examples from age
these are actual pieces of forward that
are effectively curios and it's it's
remarkable how they map to
well I'll skip ahead a little bit but
when you get to the to the mathematical
definition of the qrf as a Quantum
system that
um you know you can specify with with
this category Theory diagram you know
you have incoming arrows into a node
that then they expands right and this
graphic correspond to measurement and
preparation degrees of not degrees of
300 degrees of freedom would be the same
right when you attach it to the boundary
but measurement and preparation stages I
guess would be the the better word ah
but
but anyways let me go back to to these
examples right
um and Daniel your the biologist here so
correct me bye say anything wrong here
you have uh
uh cartoon picture of a bacteria I think
and
this is a very simple sort of thing
right it navigates in in the direction
of food
and and that's it right so it is a very
simple rudimentary example of a curve
you have the sensory
uh
stage here I guess the degrees of
freedom I guess the degrees of freedom
um it's not obvious here what the
boundary is that's one thing uh but it
is a good enough picture to see the
resemblance to here we have the
measurement
which in this in this case you're trying
to measure concentration of food you
have your node here
scene
which is your prior distribution for
concentration of food
and finally you have the the preparation
stage
which is your
you know this the rest of this chemical
Network that will control
uh and steer this bacterium right so
there's here you want to call it the
action degrees of freedom
um that will steer this bacteria in the
direction of food
and likewise with cell division this I
understand even less the network appears
more complicated uh but I think it's
fair to say that at the end of the day
all these chemical Networks
that appears super complicated
somehow have to be mapped to this
category theoretical diagram that's
that's all there is to it you're going
to have the sensory input and the action
output
again you're gonna have to
the default chemical concentration which
amounts to this to this node over here
you remember this from last lecture
right Daniel yeah in the cone cocon we
explored also in in live stream 17 on
the Bayesian semantic information flow
but I'll kind of add a point about these
biological systems
um in relationship to to artificially
specified systems and what that helps us
understand about perception cognition
action so the cone cocone diagram has
this bow tie architecture or this kind
of like two pyramids touching point to
point where there's a preparation and a
measurement which can be
um different dimensionalities or or
different Scopes like you could be
multi-input multi-output or multi-input
single output vice versa and so on but
they come through this
eye of the needle with C Prime here now
contrast that kind of architecture
um represented here abstractly with what
we see in the bacterial process and in
the cell division process these have
that kind of a bow tie perception
cognition action architecture or
measurement cognitive integration
preparation architecture
in contrast we see for example an
artificial neural network where the
input and the output layers are usually
lower dimensional maybe uh in an image
coming in with several hundred pixels
and a single output like a classifier
coming out the other end but a
dimensional explosion in those internal
cognitive layers but in biological
systems it's actually exactly the
opposite for example many many many
receptors on the cell surface on the
holographic boundary the sensorium of
the cell but then there are these common
secondary Messengers
that many Pathways converge upon
so that reflects the kind of radically
different
architecture that a qrf embodies as
opposed to the approach taken by
disembodied intelligence Frameworks
which use dimensional explosion
internally
to try to categorize and classify and
find find edge cases versus this
dimensional winnowing that is reflective
of these embodied intelligences
um
anybody make a tangential comment here
also no I think the good thing about
these two examples is that they also
showcase
the fact of how how you know
the the Deep implications of scale free
biology if you want to call it this way
we tend to think of
these sorts of processes right of such
as here
only happening at the level of the
nervous system in animals or as you said
neural nerves right we tend to associate
this with neural networks and and
perhaps Evolution has tear does in a way
that's
um endowed us with nervous systems to
make these things maybe these are higher
up in the in the in the layers
uh but really there is you know that's a
bit of an arbitrary distinction that we
make you know the process is going on at
the cellular level even if they don't
appear to have anything to do with the
nervous system
my understanding is that uh they are
there are there are some generic
properties that are the same and
everything that has to do with
information processing you know it
manifests maybe a slightly different
uh when it comes to explicit nerves but
at the end of the day it's the same
generic process going on would you would
you say that's right Daniel
the the ontological claim is that it's
the same generic process happening
whereas the more instrumentalist claim
is that we can model it with some shared
abstractions
[Music]
yeah okay so we can we can continue
right
um
so
uh
from you know I I don't have a whole lot
to say Daniel
said quite a bit about at the end of the
day craft is is you can visualize it as
this diagram and you know you can think
of it as if you are more familiar with a
picture of a neural network and ways on
a neural network and so on that's the
way to think about it
now let's continue with explicit
embodiment if you wish uh so qrfs in in
the formalism have to be attached to
a boundary boundary degrees of terms and
I should add another remark here I think
and personally to me also like the hard
part about uh
this Quantum free energy principle
formalism if you wish is is what you
said at the beginning is the fact that
it's topological right so so very often
it's not clear what the boundary degrees
of freedom of right because we tend to
think of boundaries as
you know
geometrical and certainly the classical
fep
s the most geometrical
uh that's not the case here in the
quantum for energy uh formalism and
where we have emerging space with us
what we talked about in later sessions
but that's just like one one quick
remark to make
at the end of the day though
even if it's topological we're going to
have real degrees of freedom that
um these
your ref is attached to this cone cocon
diagram
and you're going to have measurement
operators that you don't
um classical outcomes
plus and minus one
and
uh
and then you can think of this PRN
um or more abstract like this diagram as
as a neural network if you wish acting
on those under qubits
and then back propagating
some sort of action signal preparation
um okay
then let's not forget that uh Land hours
principle
and so on
requires that we are mindful of energy
constraints on computation
and that gives us
the following picture
uh number one we're gonna have to
use energy from the environment to fuel
our computation to fill our observation
so that means that right away you cannot
use the entirety of your boundary to
gather information you're there's it
necessitates a uh
an allocation of resources right
uh
here e is the observed environment and
the blue portion is a thermodynamical
sector
where you extract free energy and and
dump key in order to run this
computational process and then
furthermore you can have
uh a memory sector where you write
things on a boundary okay and these
takes up energy also right driving
information on onto the boundary by
Latin hours principle will take up
information
and uh critical is the minimal interest
in observer
because it has a memory sector and why
minimal here uh implies that we have at
least minimal interesting implies that
we have more than one layer here the
process of writing things into the
into a memory sector
requires us to have a clock so that we
can label those memories
um in time okay so we do have time as
part of this formalism just not space
yet okay no time has to be
internal to the help server
just just one piece on that that Chris
mentioned
um as and as you echoed time here is an
attribute of some cognitive systems in
terms of their internal understanding so
that they can sort memories and
understand what came earlier or later
it's not something that's a priori
defined externally which is the case in
the kind of space time first now how do
we fit communication into here
we flip that we're talking about the
topology of communication as
ontologically primal
and now certain kinds of sophisticated
agents that's not like necessarily true
of a rock or a metronome or a particle
of a gas but some kinds of cognitive
systems are such that they are able to
generate an internal clock concept
and that doesn't have to be the same
thing as what's happening on the wall
with Chronos this can reflect a purely
internal time Kairos that enables
observers or interactors that have
different clock structures and then Land
hours principle helps us Arbitrage or
connect the informational demands to the
energetic or the metabolic demands Dean
oh so when I when I first listened to
the lecture I thought when the when the
term or phrase trade-off
was raised I
I traditionally have thought of tradeoff
as kind of a binary
if I'm picking this
I'm trading off against all the other
things that I didn't pick
so one or or the other or others plural
but when I saw when I saw this and
especially when I heard it in the
context of things like degrees of
freedom I began to wonder whether it is
because it could sit on either side of
that boundary it could be a priori or it
could be ad hoc or post-talk a trade-off
which prior to
this conversation I just assumed that a
trade-off was one or the other
but essentially what this implies is it
it isn't even it's still a kind of a
degree of
of how much weight you put into it and
then it you kind of cross a threshold
and then you've made your pick you've
you've completed your trade-off or did I
again
did I misinterpret what I was hearing if
it's if it's topological as opposed to
this the more conventional space-time
perspective
is this can can a trade-off be both ad
hoc and post hoc
seemingly at the same time
very interesting question
let us just let it float and continue on
enter all right because maybe because
again if it's if it I'll just say this
if it if it can be that
that would really move us out of the
classical Realm
that would essentially say that anytime
we've made a pick we re we really
haven't made a pick
there's still a whole bunch of other
things that are going to happen that can
that can change whatever that
action is that we thought we
carried out or enacted if we're talking
about in in an internet intern
internality state
which is what I think we want I think we
want to be able to change our minds
but let me take that one way Dean
um the the analytical equations of the
action perception Loop
don't tell us in implementation like if
we're going to write it in code whether
we should
use action first
procedurally to update our observations
or whether we enable our observations to
to Wag the Dog and then select action at
the end of the loop so is it a
perception action Loop or is an action
perception Loop and those enable a kind
of um seesaw where sometimes we want
what we learn to change what we do and
other times we want what we do to change
what we learn
and having that kind of a fulcrum or a
pivot
and then again to connect it to the
vertex popping in and out the analytical
formalisms inscribed on the screen of
the fep like the textbooks
they're ambiguous
whether we lead with action and have
inference follow or whether we lead with
inference and and have action follow or
or simply without should have inference
follow whichever one of the combinations
there are
um because we s and then the that
um trade-off or runoff is broken by
specific embodied cognitive agents that
that trade-off about the um the
procedural Primacy of perception or
action
can't be broken generically right
it certainly makes for a lot of waste
heat if you're not careful
it'd be exhausting a lot anyway
okay so um
so I I see I I don't know if we can talk
about
intent
um much with this formalism but we can
take a very descriptive uh approach to
it and
um go down here a little more
uh actually before I don't want to get
up I'm ahead of myself uh what I mean by
that is
I
whether we can put intent or not in this
hierarchy
um I I don't know I don't know if it
matters a whole lot but at least we can
talk about it you know operationally and
descriptively and and say just like
when you have a clock
uh
you know that the clock is just there
right like it is it if you don't have
the clock you don't have the memory and
that's it right uh and likewise here if
we don't have attention
uh an attention control compartment we
just cannot have we cannot play with all
these cure apps uh that are
non-commutative
at the same time
so
if there is no attention control system
to begin with no we don't we cannot talk
about a system that has non-commutative
care apps meaning here one one
presumably goes to memory sectors the
other one goes to environment side
persons and so on uh so
so this is certainly a necessity of the
fact that we have
um different sectors of the boundary
being allocated to different purposes
such as environmental observation and
memory and so on
um within the environment it was
it's it's worth remarking that here if
you if you think deeply about first
principles and
what it means to observe an entity
um well you still come down to these
differences that make a difference sort
of thing right which involves whenever
you're looking at the environment to if
you're gonna identify a system you need
sort of a background that tells you
that puts the system in context right so
that you can identify the system as some
something distinct I think this again is
something that we have talked about in
previous
uh discussions where the easiest picture
here is something like the gauge speed
gauge in your car where
p is the gauge itself it tells you
the speed
but it's meaningless
without the reference system right
outside of outside of the thing that
stays invariant right the context the
background
um
that Gauge Movie means nothing to you
okay so the command come back to this
idea of if we think of information as
differences that make a difference in
terms of first principles these
environment sector that we saw earlier
has to be further broken down into
pointer on reference to States
again this is covered uh in depth in the
increases papers uh I'm thinking
particularly of
free energy for generic Quantum systems
uh and again uh just to reiterate these
attention control stuff uh compartment
which is by the way very reminiscent too
the hierarchy that was earlier with the
clock uh arising fire up in the
hierarchy deeper into the layer
um
likewise whenever we have so whenever
you're writing something into into a
memory you need you need to have that
clock whenever you are deploying
uncommunicated graphs you're you're
gonna need
uh attention
an attention control compartment and we
just described this operationally
um
if you didn't have it then the agent
would not be what it is it could not
deploy those non-communitive QRS
uh so marching on
uh we'll just end here with uh pure app
alignment on the free energy principle
just a few more words this is possibly
the most interesting picture in this in
this uh presentation and just we can
recall here uh possibilities for qrf
alignment and how
through energy comes into play in this
in this um formalism
so is that recall we call a the true
real interaction we call this a thermal
interaction
and and then you have a bunch of
possibilities right and depending on
each possibility you're going to see
things as
uh notes or as in the paper says
non-local
given variables
uh the last situation is
uh
what we call alignment when we have qrfs
of the same size perfectly aligned
okay
to attack by recall I think this
this would be the situation where you
have uh
noiseless
classical uh computation right if you
have a and b just interacting
you know
and uh it also also this is the
situation where
this is
this is entanglement right
asymptotically once all the carers are
aligned you you have entitled and now we
can type but maybe
to Deans earlier so these two these two
slides conclude the discussion basically
and then we can open it up
um so given this possibilities for how
qrfs can be aligned
here is deployed by a become via line
uh and how you know in each situation
you're going to get noise or whatever
um
then what does
the free energy principle say in this
Quantum setting
well
minimizing variational free energy leads
you to entanglemental okay so if
theorem here
if you're in a picture of B here and the
qrfs are are aligned
uh A and B are going to be intact
now there is a tension between this
tendency towards alignment uh us the
pre-energic principle
will carry you and uh
observe reality which is that we're not
just a blob of entangled particles there
is separability
and
systems are attention between
maintaining separability
um and at the same time being correlated
enough to the environment
just to be able to predict predict it or
come
and now we can maybe go into a more
philosophical discussion about the free
energy principle
um I should also say
in the last month I just like I talked
earlier at traps
um
it led me into a rabbit fall of looking
into his recent work and he's talked a
lot about complexity uh I'm being very
speculative here so I if someone can
call me out uh that would be good in the
comments but Justice coming through some
of his papers I saw a monograph of 2018
where he talks about complexity and
you know he puts forward the second law
for complexity in Quantum systems and
increased complexity and it is very
reminiscent of what's going on here you
have a tension between
uh systems tending to entanglement
beyond the other side of the free energy
function well if you wish were systems
increase in complexity and that
necessarily requires uh
that A and B are separate
So Daniel do you have any comments at
this point
yeah there's a lot to it I I like that
you showed the four possibilities
in the image above and and said it was a
one of the most interesting figures I I
agree
and uh
how to connect this to the classical fep
and also how to
see the quantum fep
not as just uh a second story built on
top of the classical fep which would be
kind of like a a historical
chronological understanding of the
theoretical apparatus but it's almost
like the quantum fep was like
a basement we didn't know about
because it it gives a broader context
and though it appeared
conceptually several years later in the
timeline we understand
that doesn't give it a secondary
um
status
so what it really means for the
classical fep
to be kind of like
a special case
of this
um
actually more
generic
setting
there's just a lot I'm very uncertain I
can I can I I can wrap it up underneath
or you want to say something
um we can continue with that but let me
conclude and this is all I have to say
for today
um
I I think I mean I'm sure Chris will
explain this more in coming uh sessions
and lectures but I think the main
key differences is in is in the
emergence of of space
how it might emerge from something more
fundamental maybe a tensor Network or
who knows uh but that's that's the big
big difference right and and I suppose
the quantum free energy principle
generalizes
the classical for energy principle
because he doesn't have this special
embedding now uh
this to me personally and and and also
to folks in the audience for asking
questions is is probably the hardest
part to wrap your head around and I
I foresee interest in in those uh
discussions and lectures that deal with
the concept of emerging space
because every time you try to connect on
it I've done this myself I've been
thinking about how you could apply these
formalism to better known pictures or
compare it for instance with thermal
equilibrium with relaxation with thermal
equilibrium and then you start thinking
about okay what is the boundary and so
on it's far from obvious right because
again you have to
remind yourself that the definition is
topological so in that regard I think it
might be worth
um
one of the questions that came up that I
thought I thought was good
and and then I can call it a day on this
end uh
so this question and I think it was the
first question asked since the last
lecture can you just read the full
question and then read the full answer
thank you the question on the answer
it's number 28 here can you guys see it
should I zoom in a little bit it's it's
pretty small but but reading it will be
good
okay so this question I think I've asked
myself this question two
um maybe with different in a different
way but basically you know it gets to
the point of what I was saying earlier
right
um that it would be nice to see how we
can use this Quantum free energy
principle formalism
to recover maybe from your settings such
as relaxation to thermal equilibrium via
ticket equation but that's far from
movies how you do it if your definition
is topological right
so the question says what happens when
the agent becomes identical to the
environment
when the model has been improved so much
that it does not differ from the
environment is this a stadium impossible
would it be thermionamical equilibrium
maximum entanglement okay so clearly
it's not thermodynamical equilibrium but
I think what the person is asking if I
maybe
if I understand this correctly they're
wondering okay so it's a free energy
principle
drives AME towards entanglement then
it's referred to say that they have that
any distinction between them has to be
solved
right that they have merged into the
same thing
um
and that has to do with this whole
definition of philosophical evade of
thinness that uh called Princeton you
know it's a proponent enough right what
it means for two things to be separate
I'm coming
so let's see what Chris said
uh
Kristen has pointed out that the limit
of the classical fep the limit of
perfect prediction corresponds to
generalized synchronic between system
and environment each sends messages but
the other can perfectly predict
uh now however it's clear and I'm not
reading anymore I'm making a quick
remark here I'll continue in a second
in the classical fep
it's clear
that A and B even if they are you know
in the perfect limit of the fep
they remain
different the different entities right
because you have that if you wish that
extra
uh layers of differentiation coming from
their spatial embedding right in the in
the classical fpp that is clear that
they haven't even if they are getting
synchronized
they have not lost their separate
identities you can always say well this
is the one that was to the left and this
is the one that was to the right pun
intended with earlier discussion right
um
you have that extra uh
resource for for separating them if you
wish by virtue of the special embedding
right the special embedding is giving
you this extra information that
allows you to keep track of of of amb
separately
okay so I'll continue this notion
depends on the system and its
environment being separated and has
distinguished somehow
In classical formulations they are
separated in ordinary 3D space
different locations so they are
different because they occupy different
locations right but if you don't have
that geometric wall
background then then how you know that
they're different right okay so I
continue
the quantum formulation is background
free meaning it assumes no space-time
embedding system and environment do not
have different locations even though
they have different sets of degrees of
freedom in the overall Hilbert space
here the fpp
the limit of the fep is maximum and time
moment
this does not mean that the system and
its environment are identical they
aren't since they have different degrees
of freedom okay so this is just
addresses the question I I just post it
means that the joint state is not
separable
okay
um into a system s an environment team
their states are no longer conditionally
independent this is distinct from
thermal equilibrium which means that
they have the same temperature while
remaining separable
uh and that their interaction can be
characterized as the change of thermal
fluctuations I.E knows
so I guess this is a nice format for
things that are to come but I I do think
that this
or idea of emerging space is going to be
um
possibly you know one of one of the most
important intercourse
stick out between the classes and the
quantum formulations for sure
Dean what's your take on this what what
I saw what I saw was that when you have
that kind of alignment that perfect
alignment that is one that was one that
was D in that diet in that
that diagram right that was one state of
a of a complex state that included an A
and A B and a c and probably a whole
bunch of other ways that
yeah right so that one
state where you've got this kind of
entanglement
isn't isn't into perpetuity like you
don't get there and then stay there and
that's where I think
the question of separability and
complexity
it still works because just because you
momentarily got into a place that we
Define here as D doesn't mean you stay
there indefinitely
you could be swapping around to B and C
and A
in the next instant
so that's that at least that holds the
complexity piece up
that that moment for however long that
moment is where XA and x b are aligned
isn't permanent
so it's it's not predictable in that
sense therefore it is complex
I still don't know how we get though
that the closer we get to agreement the
more complex Things Are
unless we're just talking about D in
this array of a b c and d
that goes back to that Quantum reference
frame I think like I said again maybe
I'm interpreting this wrong but when I
message pass
the reason why I have to like literally
give it over to the other person and let
them have it I can't give have them copy
what I'm doing
is because there has to be
I guess that reinforces the separability
piece of this as well the fact that I
can't give them a copy that I can only
give them the information and then
they've got to sort of unpack it in
their own
in their own way of taking it off the
the boundary but again
I struggle with this I'm
guilty as charged but I am I am what I'm
trying to do is trying to come up with
my own narrative so that what Chris is
saying
makes sense to me as opposed to make
sense to the world which is what Chris
is trying to do
I'll try with another speculative
fiction
so
um there's a screen
between let's just say the stage and the
audience or whatever it's a holographic
screen and on each side of the screen
there's some
embodied object
so that means that it must have um Vault
it's a volume and closing object because
points and lines and planes are only
abstractions every real physical object
encloses volume and now a light is going
to be coming from behind each object
facing the screen and that's this kind
of
uh cone that we're seeing from each side
it's like the shadow cast by the object
so if the object was a sphere then it
would be projecting down to a circle
onto the screen if the shape were a cube
it could be
projecting down and so where the light
is positioned
is the um perspective that that
cognitive entity is taking on its qrf
those lights could move so now we have
the situation where the two spotlights
are moving maybe the shapes are staying
the same maybe they're changing too
and it's like two searchlights scanning
across this
B oval
and some sometimes they are perfectly
locked I mean there could be a situation
where they're perfectly aligned
or there could be situations where
they're totally disjoint
um and each of those situations have
different implications
for
what one entity sees
when it looks at the screen maybe like
the shadow is the only part where you
can see
because the rest of it is too blinding
or something like that and so then if
we're in case a here where
um maybe B doesn't have a projection or
maybe B's projections totally somewhere
else then a is in this solipsistic I'm
the active agent interacting within an
art World setting
and D is like
potentially the
um the computer Engineers classical
dream or asymptote which is like all the
data going through the USB cable is just
being perfectly noiselessly received
and then we also get these um B and C
cases
but a is kind of like the inner world
D is like the
perfect Communication channel and then
to connect it just to friston's concept
of generalized synchrony as we've talked
about many times generalized synchrony
doesn't mean lockstep two agents could
reduce their uncertainty about each
other not by doing the same thing at
every time step but for example by turn
taking and I think that points the way
to how we get reduction of variational
free energy reduction of prediction
error surprise and so on without
especially spatial temporal enmeshment
but not necessarily even informational
identity in measurements because you
could have two things that through their
alignment
become actually differentiated and that
could increase the mutual information
between two metronomes not just to have
them going in the same direction but to
have them going in in opposite
directions the mutual information in
those two settings is going to be high
so it's not the case a generalized
synchrony means that
um things are becoming
uh
blurred
we could actually also have integrated
information through
increased
articulation not just decreased
and then
life finds a way or cognition finds a
way
on this trade-off Frontier of in our
pursuit of unitarity
will we blur to unify or will we
differentiate to unify but those are the
paths we have we don't have the um
backwards ratchet
yeah
yeah makes sense
any other ladder slides enter
uh no that's it uh so Chris made a few
more remarks at the end about uh
language
here uh but you mentioned that he's
gonna talk more about this in the coming
lecture so we'll just leave it up to him
yeah there could be some very
powerful and interesting
linguistic
opportunities
for updating
our speaking to reflect what we are
learning
here
I don't know what those necessarily are
whether it's a syntactic or a semantic
thing or whether it's a narrative
thing
but how to actually re-enter
some of these formalisms into our
Focus understanding
could just be immensely powerful and um
we could have a lot of Integrity between
the natural language way that
potentially we're already showing up for
engagement
and some of these formalisms
that
gets a first principles about
interacting entities and boundary
conditions and all of that
Dean any penultimate thoughts
not really I I'm going to go back and
listen to the
I'm going to listen to Chris's comments
again about this common cause and the
fine-tuning Assumption and whether
that's sort of a
metaphorically a dialing in or what it
what he means exactly by the fine tuning
in the in the context of this
conversation today what you just kind of
said about are we dulling something here
or are we sculpting something to make it
more fittable
like I'm going to go and now and go back
and listen to what he talks about in
terms of fine tuning and maybe update my
priors around that so
enter any last uh thoughts or maybe
scroll over to the um schedule the
course again just so we can close on
that
yeah we're halfway through we just
completed the third discussion section
now so we've had three lectures and
three discussions it's all downhill from
here
um by the way this was the first midterm
you guys both did well
um we're gonna head into four or like
session four with these last three how
agents use multiple communication
channels and that's going to get
connected to the quantum fep how space
time emerges from communication which is
something that we've brought up a bunch
it's been in the background but but
making That explicit it's going to be
exciting and then section six I think is
just gonna be
such a jumping off point
because the scope
and the intensity of what is transpiring
is Extreme
so connecting it to biology
which is to say life more fully and
where we go in in 23 and Beyond
that's going to be awesome so any last
words Ender
uh no I just think of what you said um
very I would I would say it's going to
be uphill in in terms of how interesting
it's going to get
cool well I encourage people to uh check
out the
course website and submit questions that
they'd like to see addressed by Chris
also to register and join these
participatory discussions there'll be
three more of them so if you want to
join share your qrf
be part of the publication of all of
these works that will compile at the end
and just get your
exoskeleton in the game
with what is happening here it'd be
really awesome to hear more voices and
and to have more on board
okay thank you Dean and Andrew till next
time